<Document>
# Psychologist/Psych Ward SOP
This is the list of procedures, responsibilities, and duties of the [color=#1b67a5][bold]Psychologist[/bold][/color] of this station.


<ColorBox>
  <Box HorizontalAlignment="Center" Margin="10">
   The sanitarium program, which moves certain criminally insane brig inmates to the medical department inside of a Psych Ward, gives Nanotrasen psychologists a newly crucial function on board NT stations.
  </Box>
</ColorBox>


1.The most important function of the Psychologist is the treatment and containment of the criminally insane inside of medical. To abandon this responsibility or prioritize other ones may result in termination.

2.The psychologist, if there are no sanitarium inmates inside medical and no crew in need of psychological/psychiatric support, may assume the duties of a regular medical doctor until a need for their position arises.

3.Sanitarium inmates are typically permanent brig inmates, and are criminally insane, a danger to themselves and others. The psychologist must do everything in their power to ensure that in their treatment of sanitarium patients, they do not enable harm to come to NT crew members aboard their station as a result of lacking restraints. Sanitarium inmates are NOT allowed outside of the medical department for the duration of their treatment.

4.Sanitarium inmates are to typically be equipped with a straitjacket, if they attempt to wriggle free of their restraints, a psychologist is expected to interrupt this process, and if repeated, sedate the patient with ketamine. The psychologist may make an exception, but keep the safety of the crew in mind when making these exceptions.

5.Sanitarium inmates are considered permanent brig inmates and all the same rules apply to them, except the psychologist, CMO, and orderlies may assume the role of security team members in space law as written.

6.Should any sanitarium patient prove too troublesome for medical staff to handle, they may be freely handed to security for safekeeping while awaiting future treatments done by more qualified medical staff.

7.Should the highest ranking member of security, or the captain, deem a sanitarium patient a risk and request a sanitarium inmate be handed over to them, the patient must be freely surrendered in proper restraints at risk of non compliance and/or endangerment brig sentences.

## Sanitarium Release

To be released from the sanitarium program, a patient must be cleared of all common psychological ailments found inside the most dangerous permanent brig inmates, then have a psychologist or CMO stamped document acknowledging their mental stability faxed to Central Command. Once this is done, the sanitarium inmate may return to their usual permanent brig to serve the rest of their sentence.

1. Placement in reality: A patient must acknowledge their place in reality. The most common delusions include the existence of some all powerful force known as "the admins" and the notion that all of reality takes place inside a simulation. Delusional patients must be thoroughly drilled until they can correctly differentiate reality from fiction. Patients are to be asked about these concepts at least once.

2. Violent Outbursts: A patient (obviously) must not be an obvious and immediate risk to their fellow man, even after being released from their restraints. Tests may include unrestraining the patient in the presence of toys, animals, non crew, or consenting NT staff. Do not allow the patient outside of medical during these tests.

3. Clearance of common triggers. A patient must demonstrate their lack of violent or delusional outbursts through being placed in a variety (at least 2 or 3) strenuous situations that would trigger an outburst, E.G having an item of value taken from their possession by security or being insulted. If the patient should fail these tests and display behaviors typial of their condition, they are to be returned to step 1 and must repeat any treatments prescribed to improve their behavior by the psychologist.

4. Written Exam: The psychologist must write and the patient must take a written exam. Each psychologist will differ in opinion on what the contents of their written exam must include. But a written exam with questions demonstrating placement in reality, proper responses to stressful situations, and general good moral character is expected to be faxxed to CC completed by the patient alongside their recommendation from the psychologist/CMO.

On completion of all these steps, a psychologist or CMO may stamp a letter of recommendation for their release. Once this is done, the inmate MUST be returned to the permanent brig. Calling security and ensuring their safe arrival in security's brig.
</Document>
